<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://elephantlaboratories.com/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<title>
ELEPHANTlaboratories
</title>
<link>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/
</link>
<description>
Life, paradox and game design
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Sun, 19 Jun 2016 13:15:40 -0700
</lastBuildDate>
<author>
Ryan Spangler
</author>
<item>
<guid>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/chronicle/posts/2015-08-04-gencon.html
</guid>
<link>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/chronicle/posts/2015-08-04-gencon.html
</link>
<title>
GENCON
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gencon2015/event.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GENCON&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;on&amp;#95;scale&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On Scale&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We got to Gencon on Wednesday to get a jump on things, and have a day to adjust before we dove into a weekend full of &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/174837/sol-last-days-star'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; demos.  We walk in the front doors of the convention hall and it doesn't seem too crazy.  Small bunches of people in snarky t-shirts wandering around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Let's just get our badges.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We walk to the entrance of the line labeled &quot;Will Call&quot;.  Doesn't seem bad, just some white satin cloth over a couple of snaking guiderails.  No problem.  But someone stops us as we try to go in.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Can't go in here, you have to go to the back of the line.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And he points us back further.  We see another line veer around a corner.  Someone is guiding the line in batches across the walkway so it doesn't block the thoroughfare.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;It starts somewhere around that bend&quot; he says.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, no problem.  Just around the bend.  So we follow around the bend, and in one revelatory moment we see the LINE.  It goes on forever.  It is like a river of people, throngs of humanity spilling in every direction.  In another hallway called the &quot;Crossroads&quot; there is another couple of ushers letting packets of the line through, making sure the line doesn't block traffic.  This line has USHERS.  And we keep going.  And going.  And gooooooooooooing.  This hallway is huge, and the line stretches its entire length.  We walk what must be the equivalent of five city blocks and still no end.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Holy crap.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally we see it.  The end.  There are a couple of volunteers in bright lime green shirts waving people there.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;The end!  You've found the end!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No, this was just the beginning. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gencon2015/creeper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GENCON&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was an eye-opening introduction to Gencon, the largest gaming convention stateside.  We spent the entire weekend boggled by the sheer scale of the thing.  Everywhere we went we were confronted with it.  Want a table to play a game?  How about THOUSANDS?  Want to go to the bathroom?  Sorry there is a parade of costumes going on right now that is blocking all passage.  Want some food?  So do 61,423 other people!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was pretty impressive.  And overwhelming.  I know we missed 99 percent of it.  But it was still awesome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;sol&amp;#95;at&amp;#95;gencon&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Sol at Gencon&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gencon2015/cool.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GENCON&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We went to Gencon with a single purpose: demo &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/174837/sol-last-days-star'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; as many times as possible.  And we did a pretty good job!  25 demos over 4 days (for comparison, Gamestorm and Kublacon both came in around 10 demos each).  In the process we met a bunch of great people.  Some of them may be you!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gencon2015/thoughtful.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GENCON&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One very different thing about Gencon from the other conventions we've been to was the lack of official open gaming tables.  Every table in the main hall was scheduled for something.  When we asked information and volunteers where the open gaming was, they were befuddled.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;You mean the Wil Wheaton talk?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No, no we did not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We spent the first two days in the game library... because that was the only place it seemed like we could play a game we had brought.  The problem with the game library was that it cost &quot;tickets&quot; to go in.  Everything at Gencon cost tickets!  It was like the Fair of games.  Luckily, there were enough people milling around that were open to playing a random game about the Sun exploding.  Thanks all, and great to meet you!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, thanks to a tip from our friend Matt from Panda, we discovered that we could after all play our game in the main event hall... we just had to schedule it with the hall &quot;HQ&quot;.  So many lessons.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gencon2015/hall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GENCON&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Man that place was insane.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;takeaway&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We knew we were getting in way over our heads even thinking about going to Gencon.  But at the same time, we just wanted to see what the hell was going on.  Sometimes it is good to do things that you are not ready for in order to rise to the challenge.  Thanks to everyone we met who made that process worthwhile.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until next year!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gencon2015/wings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GENCON&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Tue, 04 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0700
</pubDate>
<author>
Ryan Spangler
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/chronicle/posts/2015-05-30-kublacon.html
</guid>
<link>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/chronicle/posts/2015-05-30-kublacon.html
</link>
<title>
Sol at KublaCon!
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Over memorial day weekend Ryan and Jodi attended KublaCon in San Francisco!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/ryan-laugh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryan Laughing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sean was unable to make it, but he was there in spirit.  Here he is on a fish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/gamestorm2014/sean-on-a-fish.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sean on a Fish&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;trajectory&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Trajectory&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a contour to a large event like this.  When we arrived at the Hyatt by the San Fransicso Airport on Thursday we took a moment to collect our wits and have some lunch in the sun and tree filled Atrium at the center of the hotel, a towering nine-story room bathed in natural light.  No one had really shown up yet and the place was pretty quiet.  We ate by the tranquility of a nearby fountain and reflected on this time of peace before a huge event.  I thought how much I savored being immersed in this quiet full of potential before all hell breaks loose.  When the event was in full steam I knew I would be too busy and caught up in things to fully appreciate what was happening, but here in the stillness of the pre-convention there was the pristine anticipation of things to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, as predicted, madness.  Flurry of humanity.  A blur of faces and outbursts and howling and joy.  Trying to find tables.  Setting things up, tearing them down, turning over cards, explaining rules, answering questions (so many questions!), flashes of color and geometry and sound.  Seeing people we just met but who are already friends.  Pointing at things.  Gesticulating wildly.  Shouting because I can't even hear myself.  Shouting because I don't even realize I'm shouting.  Stumbling around for food, still dizzy from games.  Sleeping in fits.  Shouting.  Drinking Chartreuse because Jodi was smart and picked some up in town.  Handing out t-shirts to enthusiastic cries.  The sun exploding, over and over and over again.  I love it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, before I even realized what was happening, suddenly the halls were empty.  No people wheeling tubs of games around.  No gesturing at pac-man tie-dyed shirts.  No lines at the flea market.  No tables upon tables of rioting color and sound.  What happened?  Siiiiiiiiiigh... what a great time!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wait, I don't get to do this again next weekend??&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;game&amp;#95;design&amp;#95;contest&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Game Design Contest&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We entered &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/174837/sol-last-days-star'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; into the KublaCon Game Design Contest, which turned out to be a pretty harrowing thing to do!  After playtesting the 22 entries for a month beforehand, &lt;a href='https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgamedesigner/2341/anthony-j-gallela'&gt;Anthony Gallela&lt;/a&gt; and his entourage of board game designers and industry professionals chose five games to be the finalists during the convention, of which &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/174837/sol-last-days-star'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; was fortunate enough to make the cut. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What this meant was that for four days all of the convention goers could blind playtest the game and offer feedback for the final judgment.  I couldn't help or explain!  I had a particularly painful moment where I witnessed a group of people suffering while struggling to figure out how to play from the cryptic rules I had previously thought were crystal clear.  Wow, that hurt.  Lesson learned there, thanks guys!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite those troubles, during an instructive and entertaining ceremony with all of the nervous candidates paralyzed with anticipation,  &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/174837/sol-last-days-star'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; was awarded 2nd place!  Anthony presented us with the esteemed Silver Kubla statue - &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/silver.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Silver!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ousted only by &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/154032/vikings-dragonia'&gt;Vikings of Dragonia&lt;/a&gt;, which we admit, looks pretty cool.  Of all games that could have possibly beat us, we feel pretty good about it.  Congratulations Mach Brothers!  Good luck in the &lt;a href='https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/761929008/vikings-of-dragonia'&gt;Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt; (happening now, check it out)!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;people&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;People&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here was a great game in the sunny atrium forest room with Jonathan, Tracy, husband and crew:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/atrium.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sol in the Atrium&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later we played a rousing game of &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/147949/one-night-ultimate-werewolf'&gt;One Night Ultimate Werewolf&lt;/a&gt; at 2am, the best time to play ONUW.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here was another great &lt;a href='/chronicle/../sol'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; demo in the bar area of the atrium:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/atrium-sunday.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Atrium Sunday with Noah, Robert, Paul and Darius&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a tight scoring game with Robert, Noah, Paul and Darius, who were a total blast.  The whole crowd was fantastic and friendly, one of the most festive events we've been to.  It felt like we were constantly meeting new people we wished lived in the same town as us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are some more down in the ballroom:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/steve-kathleen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steve, Kathleen and Noah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Steve and Kathleen were old college friends, and there is Noah again.  How many times did you play &lt;a href='/chronicle/../sol'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt;?  Congratulations to you.  I don't even think that guy in the blue shirt was playing, he just wandered in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also met these guys the first night we were there (some of the only people who were around Thursday night!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/chris-andy-patrick.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chris, Andy and Patrick&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patrick, Andy and Chris.  They were our home base.  Thanks again Chris for letting me borrow &lt;a href='http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/66362/glen-more'&gt;Glen More&lt;/a&gt;.  Also, thanks to Chris and Andy for making me feel like my game collection was not actually out of control.  1200 games???  You win my friend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jodi hung out with the guys from &lt;a href='http://www.fccfreeradio.com/podcasts/tuesday/geekline/'&gt;Geekline&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/geekline.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Geekline&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Shane and Chad pictured here, John and Stephen out of frame).  They had a bunch of great advice for us (when they weren't screwing each other over) and also invited us to be on their show.  Thanks guys!  Great to meet you, and looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Megan had the coolest elf ears of all the people that demoed &lt;a href='/chronicle/../sol'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; last weekend:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/chronicle/img/sol/kublacon2015/elf.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Three Towers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She also crushed the three older guys she was playing with.  Well deserved!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were some other key people that somehow we didn't get pictures of.  Peter, Melisa and Kurt?  Love you guys!  Thanks for rocking our Sol t-shirts at the convention and beyond.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kennith!  Great to meet you.  Thanks for all the awesome diagrams that clarify what the hell is going on in our info diagram.  We are coming to the redwoods to visit.  Count on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;thank&amp;#95;you!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Thank you!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;KublaCon 2015.  What a blast.  Thanks to all the great people we met down there and all the players who demoed &lt;a href='/chronicle/../sol'&gt;Sol&lt;/a&gt; and gave us such positive feedback.  Truly an unforgettable experience.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;See you next year!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Sat, 30 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700
</pubDate>
<author>
Ryan Spangler
</author>
</item>
<item>
<guid>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/chronicle/posts/2015-03-27-birth-call.html
</guid>
<link>
http://elephantlaboratories.com/chronicle/posts/2015-03-27-birth-call.html
</link>
<title>
We are life
</title>
<description>
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;the&amp;#95;first&amp;#95;braying&amp;#95;call&amp;#95;of&amp;#95;the&amp;#95;elephant&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The first braying call of the Elephant&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every animal at some point makes its first noise, its first announcement of existence.  I personally have made many since, but I don't remember my first.  Was it triumph?  Pain?  Bewilderment?  Joy?  Or maybe just the involuntary expression of a creature with newly found vocal cords.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, this is the first call of Elephant Laboratories.  It may be considered similarly without specific content or meaning, but more a fundamental expression of existence.  Many years from now, like my own first emission, I will probably have no memory of this.  But for now, this is all I have.  This is my sentiment.  We exist.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700
</pubDate>
<author>
Ryan Spangler
</author>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
